Guide to the Helen Varney Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Helen Varney papers
1947-2015
MS 2040
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
19 boxes
The papers document the career of Yale School of Nursing professor, Nurse-Midwifery Specialty, Helen Varney Burst. The bulk of the materials are evenly divided between speeches given by Varney Burst, 1970-2015, mainly on the history or future of midwifery, and material documenting her work on the Special Commission on Infant Health in New Haven, primarily 1987-1995. There are also small amounts of material on other aspects of nurse-midwifery and Varney Burst's career.
Varney, Helen
Scope and Contents
The papers document the career of Yale School of Nursing professor, Nurse-Midwifery Specialty, Helen Varney Burst. The bulk of the materials are evenly divided between notes, drafts and final texts of speeches given by Varney Burst, 1970-2015, mainly on the history or future of midwifery, and material documenting her work on the Special Commission on Infant Health in New Haven, primarily 1987-1995. There are also small amounts of material on the short-lived Family Childbirth Center of New Haven, 1981-1986, family planning, 1967-1970, historical information on the Rooming-In program at Grace-New Haven Hospital, 1947-1962, biographical information on Varney Burst and other aspects of nurse-midwifery.
Biographical / Historical
Helen Varney Burst is professor emerita of the Yale School of Nursing, Nurse-Midwifery Specialty. After attending University of Kansas (BSN, 1961) and Yale University School of Nursing (MSN, 1963) she practiced midwifery in a variety of settings and directed nurse-midwifery education programs at the University of Mississippi Medical Center and the Medical Center of South Carolina before returning the Yale School of Nursing where she was a faculty member from 1979 until retirement in 2004.
Varney Burst is the author of the first textbook for nurse-midwives in the United States. Originally titled Nurse-Midwifery, it is now in its fourth edition as Varney's Midwifery. In addition to numerous journal articles, she is also author of Yale School of Nursing: Celebrating 90 Years of Excellence and co-author of Varney's Pocket Midwife. She was also a co-originator of the mastery learning modular curriculum design for nurse-midwife education at the University of Mississippi Medical Center in 1972.
An outspoken advocate of midwifery as a profession, Varney Burst was a member of the American College of Nurse-Midwives (ACNM), serving two terms as president (1977-1981), as chair of several committees, and as a representative to many other national groups. She received the ACNM Hattie Hemschemeyer Award in 1982. She has given many speeches and panel presentations on both the history and the future of nurse-midwifery in the United States.
Varney Burst was also involved in the efforts to improve health care for women and children in the New Haven area. She served on the Prenatal Care Committee of the Special Commission on Infant Health in the 1980s and 1990s, working to decrease the infant mortality rates in the city.
Arrangement
The material is arranged by topic and is in alphabetical order therein, except for the speeches, which are in chronological order.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Helen Varney Burst, 2015.
Midwifery; Childbirth; Family planning; Nursing -- Study and teaching; Infants -- Mortality; Varney, Helen; Yale University. School of Nursing
- General, 1961-2004
  - Correspondence
    - 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Minnesota, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ob.Gyn.News, 1983 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cognitive Dissonance: Interpreting and Implementing Faculty Practice Roles in Nursing Education, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jarrett, Armentia, and Madre, California nurse-midwife trial, 1961-1963, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Interview conducted by Helen Varney, 1991 September 3; 1 (Box 2)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - National League for Nursing accreditation, 1980 April-October (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Quickening board minutes, 1972-2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Report of the Faculty Practice Plan Task Force, Yale University School of Nursing, 1983 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Special Collection Advisory Group, 1999-2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "YSN Midwifery Students in South Africa," report by Terri Clark, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Yale School of Nursing Clinical Track Proposal, 1992 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Yale University School of Nursing Program Development I -- Preliminary", 1988 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Biographical, 1961-2005
  - Articles, clippings, and reviews, 1973-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, curriculum vita, grants, awards, 1961-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Diers, Donna, ed., Celebrating the Contributions of Academic Midwifery: A Symposium on the Occasion of the Retirement from the Faculty of the Yale School of Nursing of Professor Helen Varney Burst, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Varney, Helen, An Exploratory Study of the Deliberative Nursing Practice, thesis, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Varney, Helen, "Nursing, Nurse-Midwifery, and the History of Nurse-Midwifery in the United States", 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Scope and Contents
    This paper was written while Varney was a trainee in the Family Planning Program for Midwives and Nurse-Midwives at King's County Hospital, Brooklyn, NY.
- Family Childbirth Center, 1981-1986, 2000
  - General, 1981-1986, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Information packet, Circa 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Family planning, 1967-1970
  - Telephone conference, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - University of Wisconsin - Extension, self-study unit, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - University of Missouri telelecture on family planning, Circa 1970; 1 (Box 5)
- Grace-New Haven Hospital Rooming-In Program historical information and articles, 1947-1962, undated (Box 4, Folder 5-6, Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  General
  Grace-New Haven Hospital is now Yale-New Haven Hospital.
- Mississippi Nurse-Midwife Project, 1970-2010 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
- Photographs, 1977-1995, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Speeches, 1970-2015
  Arrangement
  Speeches are arranged in chronological order.
  There is a draft of one article included in the speeches, "Decision Making in Labor and Delivery," 1980.
  - Family Planning, Mississippi Nurses' Association (MNA), Maternal-Child Health Conference, panel moderator, 1970 April 9 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "How to Design a Mastery Learning Modular Curriculum," plenary speech, University of Mississippi Medical Center, 1973 December 9 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Harmonious Unity," on installation as president of American College of Nurse-Midwives (ACNM), 1977 May 4 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Labor Note," Medical University of South Carolina, 1977 August 21 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Adolescent Pregnancies and Problems," International Confederation of Midwives, 18th Triennial Conference, Jerusalem, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "On the Essentiality of Professional Midwives in Any Good Maternity Plan", 1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Remarks, seminar commemorating the 60th anniversary of Maternity Center Association, 1978 April (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Presidential speech, Phoenix, Arizona, 1978 May 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "The American College of Nurse-Midwives: A Professional Organization," panel presentation, 2nd annual meeting, Nurses Association if the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (NAACOG), 1979 March 19 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "What Price Visibility?," president's address, 24th annual meeting, ACNM, Miami Beach, 1979 May 2 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Speech presenting Hattie Hemschemeyer Award to Ernestine Wiedenbach, 1979 May 2 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "What is the Appropriate Training for Midwives and Should They Be Licensed?," National Association of Parents and Professionals for Safe Alternatives in Childbirth (NAPSAC), 1979 July 16 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Testimony, Legislative Program Review and Investigations Committee, Connecticut, 1979 September 4 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "Alternative Delivery Sites and the Role of Midwives," 5th Annual Ignatz Semmelweis Seminar, 1979 September 15 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "Value the Child: Focus on the Mother," panel presentation, National Continuing Education Conference for Nurses, 1979 October 10 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - "Nurse-Midwifery: Powerlessness and Power," panel presentation, Nurses as Women, 1979 November 3 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "Maternity Services: Past, Present, Future," panel presentation, 1979 November 12 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - "Decision Making in Labor and Delivery", 1980 (Box 7, Folder 17A)
    This is a draft of an article for C.C.C. newletter. The bulk of the material is taken verbatim from Varney's textbook, Nurse-Midwifery.
  - "Our Destiny," presidential address, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Testimony, Public Health Committee, Connecticut, 1980 February 28 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Testimony, Board of Medical Examiners, New Jersey, 1980 March 26 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - "Gauntlets Thrown and Caught," presidential address, 1980 September (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Varney annotated this as "the only one not published".
  - Midwifery Practice in the 1980s," Ob-Gyn Grand Rounds, 1980 November 3 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Testimony, Joint Committee on Public Health, Connecticut, 1981 February 24 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - "25 Years of Family Centered Nurse-Midwifery at Yale," Yale School of Nursing Alumnae Day, 1981 June 5 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - "Midwifery in the Americas," plenary speech, 17th Congress of the Pan American Medical Women's Alliance, 1981 September 3 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - "Overview of Educational Programs," session speech, Regional Program Orientation, March of Dimes, 1981 November 9 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - "Adolescent Pregnancy: A Worldwide Problem," Ob-Gyn Grand Rounds, University of Vermont, 1981 December 8 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - "Out -of-Hospital Birth Alternatives," International Childbirth Education Association, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Presentation, ACNM Chapter 1, Region 1, 1982 April 21 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Nurse-Midwifery: The Evolution of an Alternative," Mt. Holyoke, 1982 May 20 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "The Effect of KU Nursing Professionalism on One Person," Kansas University (KU) Nurses Alumni, Alumni of the Year speech, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "Women's Health Care in the 1980s," Women in Focus: Health Care Challenges for the 1980s, 1983 March 19 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "Technology's Impact on the Specialties", 1985 June 6 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "The Normal, Essentially Healthy 85%," National Conference on Women's Health, 1986 June 17 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Doctoral Dilemma panel discussion, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Commencement address, Georgetown University School of Nurse-Midwifery Program, 1987 December 13 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "Shoulder Dystocia," North Central Bronx Hospital, 1988 February 18 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
    Material includes slides.
  - Second Therese Dondero Memorial Lecture, ACNM Convention, Detroit, Michigan, 1988 April 24 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Ob-Gyn Grand Rounds, State University of New York (SUNY) Downstate, 1988 October 3 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Testimony, Public Health Committee,Connecticut, 1989 March 14 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - "Shoulder Dystocia: Predictors, Diagnosis, Management," ACNM, 1990 May 17 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Fourth Therese Dondero Memorial Lecture, ACNM Convention, Atlanta, Georgia, 1990 May 30 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Parkland graduation, 1990 September 24 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Commencement speech, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, 1990 December 13 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - King/Drew Nurse Midwifery Education Program keynote graduation speech, 1991 September 5 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - "The American College of Nurse-Midwives: Representing an Ancient Profession Reborn in Contemporary Society," National Institutes of Health and ACNM, 1991 October 11 (Box 8, Folder 20-21)
  - "The History and Future of Certified Nurse Midwives as Primary Care Providers in the United States," Bureau of Health Professions (BHPr), Division of Nursing (DON) and Bureau of Health Care Delivery and Assistance (BHCDA), The National Health Service Corps (NHSC), 1992 March 19 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - University of Texas at El Paso and Texas Tech University, 1993 May 5 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - American College of Nurse-Midwives Open Forum, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Therese Dondero Lecture, 1995 May 27 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "The Presidents Speak", 1995 May 29 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - "Documenting Traditions of the Past: Preserving the History of American Nurse-Midwifery," panel presentation, 1995 May 31 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Northeast Regional Council on Education for Nurse-Midwifery (NERCEN) history speech, 1995-2004 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Graduation party address, U.S.Air Force and Georgetown University, 1996 December 15 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Air Force history and closing ceremony speech, 1997 December 12 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - University of Rhode Island (URI) graduation speech, 1998 May 14 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "Yale University School of Nursing: Lux et Veritas," Yale University School of Nursing (YSN) 75th anniversary, 1998 June 6; 1 (Box 10)
  - Therese Dondero Lecture, Maine, 1998 July 31 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Therese Dondero Lecture slides listing, 1998 August 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Baystate graduation speech, 1998 December 12 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Northeast Regional Council on Education for Nurse-Midwifery (NERCEN) history speech, 1998-2006 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "So You Want to Publish a Book," ACNM presentation, 2000-2002 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "Critical Commonalities in Midwifery Education," International Conference of Midwives (ICM), 2002 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Historical Perspectives of Nurse-Midwifery in the U.S.," Kansas, 2002 March 2 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Connecticut League of Nurses (CLN)-Yale School of Nursing (YSN) history display, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "Facilitating Student Learning in the Clinical Setting," Ontario, 2004 February 12 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "Facilitating Student Learning in the Clinical Setting," clinical teaching, ACNM presentation, 2004-2005 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Columbia University 50th Anniversary of Midwifery Masters Program, 2005 May 5 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - "Bloom, Thrive, Nourish, Survive," University of New Hampshire, 2006 April 21 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Nurse-Midwifery History and You," Northeast Regional Council on Education for Nurse-Midwifery (NERCEN)/NEMEC, 2007-2008 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - "Are We Ready?," Frontier School of Midwifery and Family Nursing (FSN), 2008 October 18 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "Does Our Nurse-Midwifery History and Our Purpose Tell Us We Are Ready?," Columbia and Yale presentation, 2010 March 22, April 23 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - "Does Our Nurse-Midwifery History and Our Purpose Tell Us We Are Ready?", 2010-2014 (Box 12, Folder 8-9)
  - Midwifery in Maine in the 1800s," Pleasant River Historical Society, Addison, Maine, 2011 June 13 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Midwifery in the 19th Century," Millbridge Historical Society, Millbridge, Maine, 2011 August 11 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - "Change as a Variable in the Practice of Midwifery: Past, Present, and Future", 2014-2015 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "Moments in the History of the ACNM," American College of Nurse-Midwives annual meeting, 2015 June 28 (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Special Commission on Infant and Child Health, 1978-2008; 1987-1995
  This group is also called the Special Commission on Infant Health and the Commission on Infant and Child Health in these papers.
  - General, 1990-1995 (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
  - Agendas, 1991-1993 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Articles and clippings, 1989-1995 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "Better Beginnings II," draft, Undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Budget, 1990-1991 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Cambridge Model, 1988, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Commission meetings, 1991-1993 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Coordinating Committee, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Coordinator's Group, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1992, 2008, undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Data base, 1980-1988 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Fairchild, Elizabeth, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Fetal and infant mortality, 1989-1993 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - First Steps, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Flyers, 1992, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Focus Group on Community Health and Education Initiatives, summary, 1993 April 23 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Forms, blank, Undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - "Governor Rowland's Block Grant Initiative", 1995 February 15 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Grant request to ACNM Foundation concerning "Presidents Speak" (not funded), 1992 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - "Guidelines for the Provision of Prenatal Care", 1991 (Box 14, Folder 10-11)
  - Hanson, Charlene, 1988-1999 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Hassles subcommittee, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Healthy Start, 1989-1992 (Box 14, Folder 14-15)
  - Immunization, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Klerman, Lorraine and Varney, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Legislative proposals and alerts, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Medical Services Committee, 1988-1993 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Meeting packets
    - Commission on Infant and Child Health, 1990-1993 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Coordinator's Group, Commission on Infant Health, 1991-1992 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Prenatal Care Committee, Special Commission on Infant Health, 1990-1992 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda, 1978, 1989-1995 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Minority Community Health Coalition Demonstration Project grant application, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1990-1995 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - "A Model of Obstetrical and Gynecological Health Care Service for the Dixwell Satellite of the Hill Health Center", 1989 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - New Haven general, 1990-1993 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Notes (handwritten), 1991-1992, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Objectives
    - Commission on Infant and Child Health, 1991-1993 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Prenatal Care Committee, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Prenatal Care and Commission on Infant Health integrated objectives, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - "Opening Doors," draft, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - "Outline: A Better Chance for Every Child (ABC)", Undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Pregnancy Healthline, 1990-1991 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Pregnancy Healthline / Infoline, 1987-1992 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Prenatal Care Committee
    - General, 1987-1992 (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
    - Contact meetings, 1991-1993 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1987-1991 (Box 17, Folder 6-7)
    - Report, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Presentations, 1987-1993 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Presentations / summary of work, 1987-1988 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Problem-Oriented Perinatal Risk Assessment System (POPRAS) Program to Reduce Obstetrical Problems and Prematurity (PROPP) in the Bronx, 1988-1991 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Problem-Oriented Perinatal Risk Assessment System (POPRAS) Request for Proposal (RFP) evaluation, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Reminder notices, 1991-1992 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Reports and summaries, 1987-1991 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation Local Initiative Funding Partners Program, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - St. Raphael's Project Mothercare dedication, 1990 November 13 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Seitz, Victoria and Nacy Apfel, " Brief Overview of Findings from a Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Mothers and Their First-Born Children", 1992 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Special Commission on Infant Health, "What Is the Commission?", Circa 1991 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Standards, 1988-1992 (Box 18, Folder 10-11)
  - Strategic planning, 1990-1991 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Substance Abuse Treatment Planning, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Substance-abusing women and their children, 1990-1992 (Box 18, Folder 14)
- Workshops, 1979-2000
  - Aggie Higgins Nutrition Workshop, 1988 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Aggie Higgins Preventing Low Birth Weight, Circa 1990 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Circle of Safety, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Clinical teaching, 1982-1994 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Mastery learning, Undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Women's Studies: Nurses as Women, with Marie Manthey, 1979 November 3 (Box 19, Folder 6)